[SPEAKER_01]: So, today's sutta, well, two suttas actually, are Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama
[SPEAKER_01]: Not picking up the sign of the mind, it is impossible that he will fulfill the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having not fulfilled the right view, it's impossible that he will fulfill the right composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having not fulfilled the right composure, it's impossible that he will give up the fetters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having not given up the fetters, it's impossible that he will realize nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the converse is that it is possible that a bhikkhu who does not enjoy association and company, who is not fond of them, and is not devoted to enjoying them, would enjoy being alone in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enjoying being alone in seclusion, it's possible that he will pick up the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Picking up the sign of the mind, it's possible that he would fulfill the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having fulfilled the right view, it's possible that he'll fulfill the right composure, and having fulfilled the right composure, it's possible that he will give up the fetters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having given up the fetters, it's possible that he will realize nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... And then the second sutta, because this was fairly short, eh... Mīgajāla says at Sāvatī, The Venerable Mīgajāla went to the Blessed One, and on arrival, having bowed to the Blessed One, sat down to one side and said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhante, one who dwells alone, one who dwells alone, so it is said.
[SPEAKER_01]: To what extent is one a lone dweller?
[SPEAKER_01]: To what extent is one dweller with a second I, with a company, with a partner, with somebody or something else?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha replied, Mīgijāla, there are forms cognizable by the eye that are desirable, lovely, agreeable, pleasant, dear in appearance, connected with sensuality and enticing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If a monk delights in them, approves of them, stands holding to them, then for him, eh... as he delights in them, approves of them, and stands holding for them, delight arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is delight, there is passion, and when there is passion, there is bondage.
[SPEAKER_01]: A monk who is bound by the fetter of delight is called the one who dwells with a second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then goes... repeat the same for the sounds, odors, tastes, tangibles, mental phenomena, the dhammas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a monk dwelling in this way, even though he frequents forests and woodland, wilderness lodgings, remote abodes with little noise and little sound, secluded, hidden from human beings, suitable for seclusion, he is still called the one who dwells with a second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is the reason for that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because craving is his second, that has not been abandoned by him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, he's called one who dwells with a second, or one who dwells with a partner.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the Buddha explains the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when there are forms cognizable by the eye, that are desirable, lovely, agreeable, pleasant, dear in appearance, connected with sensuality and enticing, but the monk does not delight in them, does not approve of them, does not stand holding to them, then for him, as he does not delight in them, doesn't approve them, does not stand holding to them, delight ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, obviously, the new delight would not be arising or being maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: With delight not being, passion is not.
[SPEAKER_01]: With passion not being, bondage is not.
[SPEAKER_01]: A monk who is disengaged from the fetter of delight is called Meghajāla, one who dwells alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is the same for sounds, other states, tangibles, mental phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says that the light for that monk ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a monk dwelling in this way, Meghajāla, even though he dwells in the neighborhood of a village, crowded with monks, nuns, male lay followers, female lay followers, kings, royal ministers, ascetics of other sects and their followers, he's still called the one who dwells alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the reason for that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because craving is his second, and that craving has been abandoned by him, therefore, he's called the one who dwells alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you just go back, and now, overall, obviously, the picture that this paints is that, yes, one needs to be physically secluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Certainly, in the beginning, needs to frequent the secluded lodgings and so on, as the, you know, many suttas often talk about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, fundamentally, that, in and of itself, will not do the work of actually uprooting the companion, the partner, the second, the root of all the problems.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Frequently secluded dwellings, learning how to delight in seclusion, learning how to how to find that peace in seclusion, it's absolutely a necessary step, so that then one can really look closer towards things that Mīgajala Sutta describes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, towards one's own delight, towards sight, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, thoughts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether one is, as it says here, whether one approves of them, stands holding to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the attitude that one inadvertently cultivates, automatically cultivates, when agreeable things are experienced through the five senses and the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the point here in this sutta, is to recognize that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are forms cognizable, that are desirable, lovely, agreeable, pleasant, dear in appearance.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're sight, sound, smell, taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're mental phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are thoughts that are agreeable, pleasant, and that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're connected with sensuality, these thoughts, and they are enticing in and of themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just how they arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how they present themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something that a monk or anybody wants to practice can change or forcefully undo or get rid of.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I keep saying to people, like, you have to stop, like, automatically trying to get rid of the things that arise pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that, automatically accepting that attitude, trying to get rid of it, you are obscuring the more subtle attitude, which is, well, you delighting, approving, holding to it, basically being involved with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could try and destroy the sights or destroy the eyes in a form of, like, a desperate denial, because you can't help but do that through, first and foremost, being affected by delighting them, by approving of them, by holding on to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as the Sutta describes, the monk needs to stop that attitude of approval, welcoming, tolerating.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not go too far out and then try to, like, prevent those things from mentally arising when they arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you can try controlling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, of course, in the beginning, yes, of course, you should withdraw yourself from the bombardment of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not because that will, in and of itself, do the work, but because that can bring you closer to recognize where your delight, where you're holding on to those things, or your gratuitous resistance, if those sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches are unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, either way you're maintaining the craving, either way you're dwelling with the second and you're not truly alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this kind of... these two suttas mirror that other sutta from Majjhima Nikaya where the Buddha describes the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I often use that simile of the two wet... the two sticks... two wet sticks in the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: They need to be physically taken out of the water first, but then they need to kind of... you need to wait for a while for them to dry.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the shore, because otherwise, like, you still won't light the fire, because they're still wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although you have taken them from the water, they're wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you start rubbing them together, there will be no sparks coming out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But only after a while, when they have sort of dried out sufficiently, one can light the fire, as the sutra says.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it refers to as long as one doesn't live withdrawn with the body, withdrawn from sensuality, obviously one's minds and thoughts will be soaking wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: If one withdraws physically from the sensuality, yes, that's a good first step, but, again, one's minds and thoughts and attitudes and welcoming and approving and delighting and relishing and hoping and looking forward to, it still keeps the mind wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those attitudes need to be abandoned for the thoughts to truly dry from the entire kind of stretch of the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the thoughts have been dried out, that's when one is capable of lighting the... developing the inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this principle holds true, like, from Sotāpatti to Arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's like... Like, we'll see.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I have a list of questions and contemplations in regard to seclusion in particular, but it's good to see, like, in this... the first sutta, Anguttara 668,
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, we mentioned this sutta in the past number of times, and I think often... yeah, it's used kind of as one of the... an alternative description, certainly something that adds to the context of what is necessary to develop the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think often people take that sutta that talks about the two factors, which is the yoniso, manasikāra and utterance of another,
[SPEAKER_01]: I think sometimes people take it, I think probably, partially, due to the certainly commentarial and traditional interpretation, they take it kind of as a matter of like a... it's like a static facts, like, okay, right, so I just need to hear the right thing at the right time and magically the insight will occur, regardless of, you know, where I'm at at that moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, obviously, not just it contradicts the whole notion of gradual training described in vast majority of the suttas, but even even the suttas where the Buddha did quickly, you know, make people sotāpānas, explain dhamma at the right time, to the right extent, even that had to follow the certain order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that, you know, he would elevate their mind by talking about heavens and then, like, bring them down by talking about the perils of sensuality and make them renounce sensuality there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, he says, oh, he would know their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would know the mind is ready.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he would teach them the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, the Buddha was known as the foremost in formulating the dhamma and teaching the others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he obviously possessed the skill to see the mind of the others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the sutra is kind of extra interesting, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do you do when you don't have the Buddha to teach you?
[SPEAKER_01]: What did monks did back then?
[SPEAKER_01]: The ones that didn't meet the Buddha directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it tells you what they did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, other sutras of the gradual training tell you as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in this case, you could see, like, so, a person starts by not seeing their own mind whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that person's lucky enough, the Buddha will see the mind for them, and it will tell it the right things, and make them abandon the right fat... right obstacles, obstructions, not entirely the fetters, that... that requires their own work later, and then they will get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there's no Buddha now, like, what do you need to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have the utterance of another and say you are not looking for faults in the teaching, you are willing to consider anything that you hear as dhamma and really get to the bottom of understanding it and the meaning behind it, not just go by the tradition, by the hearsay and so on,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the other requirement?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the other requirements if you don't take that to mean... the two factors to mean, just as I said, like these static facts of just hearing the right thing at the right time and have a special experience that equates to sotāpati?
[SPEAKER_01]: And this sutta describes that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's impossible to fulfill the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible if you are not able to see the signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're not able to see your mind for what it is, correctly, in its characteristics, its features, it's impossible for you to develop the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be impossible for you to see the mind correctly, to see the feature, to see the nimitta, the signs of it, if you are not enjoying being alone in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you won't enjoy being alone in seclusion, if you're fond of company, association, entanglement, interactions with people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is, like, obviously, this sutta is already addressed to bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's already addressed to people that would have left the household life.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already addressed to people that would have been celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would not have been interacting in the, you know, the villagers' ways, as the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they, now, having given up the coarse, obviously, obstacles, obstructions, now they also have to start giving up that enjoyment in association, even if it's a wholesome association and wholesome company, not necessarily, like, really, really coarse or depraved and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, simply depending on the company needs to now be undermined, needs to be understood and needs to be replaced by actually preferring seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that you can get to see the signs of the mind, so that you can actually get that right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this paired with the suttas that describe the gradual training, kind of fits together and shows you, okay, this is how people would have trained.
[SPEAKER_01]: People that, as I said, they were not guided directly by an Arahant or by the Buddha, you know, heard some instruction here and there, out of faith, decided to go in that direction, and sometimes even maybe didn't even have, like, not even hundredth of what we have today in terms of the texts and instructions, yet it was enough for them to develop the right view and to become Arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, obviously, they were doing the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: The work being withdrawal from the coarse impurities
[SPEAKER_01]: And even in a household life, again, you could do the same, follow the same steps and what these suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't necessarily need to become a monk for it, but you need to meet the requirements.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what are the requirements of the bhikkhus?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, we all know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You meet those requirements.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, okay, your household life might be crowded and dusty, as the suttas would say, but within that,
[SPEAKER_01]: You could work or you could certainly start becoming less and less dependent on association.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you do have a choice to associate yourself or not, do you choose to to stay alone or do you choose to follow the desire for company?
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, company will be... you'll be pushed into the association, you will have to go through stuff, work, people, family, but the times when you don't have to do it, do you choose it still?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or actually, do you start choosing seclusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: And do you start working towards learning how to enjoy seclusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because nobody enjoys seclusion to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if people enjoy seclusion, there's puthujjana, it might be, you know, maybe because for one reason or the other they did not become that dependent on the company, but also it might be because they're averse to company.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not going to be a wholesome reasons for a seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to... you need to actually start re-evaluating those.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, as I said, if they're wholesome, great, but more often than not, it's going to be something other at play.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, most people will have to work towards learning how to correctly, for the right reasons, enjoy seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: How not to distract themselves from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How not to, kind of, sort of, like, use it to mask, actually, where the real work is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the point to recognize here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not going to enjoy it immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to work towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can start working towards it, is when you stop choosing company, when you are presented with choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have an option to stay alone, to stay alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have longer options to be withdrawn from people, take them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to practice this when you can, because otherwise, in a household setting, most of the time, it's going to be crowds and others and duties.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's still possible, but the fact that the household environment is different than the monk's environment,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just gonna make it harder.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not make it, like, justifiable to think or invent a different way to get to the same thing, because there isn't a different way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gradual training is the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, whether a person can achieve periods of seclusion in their home or something, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: If not,
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe go to a monastery or go somewhere on your own when that's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, use it pretty much to start reflecting in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to go through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a whole list of, like, reflections and things and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, I think it's kind of important to recognize that the question is not just about withdrawing yourself physically from people, from the association, and to feel like, okay, now my work is done, when is the Sotāpati coming my way?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, it comes when you develop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and also, yeah, another thing to mention before we go into question, it's like,
[SPEAKER_01]: When it says seclusion...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, say you begin with the seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You begin by withdrawing yourself from the company.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily, you know, maybe you're not on the level of, like, still discerning all the attitudes of delighting towards the prospects of saṃsāra-samādhi-sthārtha, what Mīgajāla Sūtra talks about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're just working on physically being withdrawn and then living with yourself for that period of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's important to recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're withdrawn into that seclusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of easy to fall into a trap of then doing the practice for the sake of basically obscuring the discomfort of seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, finding things to do, reading the suttas, studying or, you know, meditating or doing techniques often become a thing that you do so that you don't have to be alone with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, more precisely, you don't have to be alone with your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that basically means you're not in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're distracting yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're not distracting yourself with extremely unwholesome stuff that you would have been doing in the world, but nevertheless, you're doing it for the same reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why we have to recognize that when you're in seclusion, when you want to develop that seclusion, yeah, of course, it's not going to be perfect, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, if you need to read something, read something, but you need to recognize that all of that has to lead to the point when you can abide in seclusion, not have or need anything to do, and be fine with yourself, and not lose the sight of your mind, the signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if suddenly you have nothing to do, you'll be absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: There would be no, like, pressure building up from that animal that's forcing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, you gotta find some occupation, because otherwise this is getting unbearable.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm drowning in myself, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is important, because, again, especially, like, you know, if you're still unsure about what the actual practice is, and maybe if you're not convinced,
[SPEAKER_01]: By our arguments, when it comes to meditation or whatever, and if you still find meditation helpful and so on, it's going to be very easy to fall into meditating in seclusion, so that you are not alone with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I've seen that happen to many people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, one acquaintance of ours, a monk, he disrobed eventually, and he would... he used to go and stay in this really remote kutis in Sri Lanka.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, super remote.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just go pindapad in the morning to the village, you don't even have to talk to anybody, and then you go back, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no electricity, no... nowhere to even go for, like, nature hikes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just absolute wilderness, hot, unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just be sitting in your kuti till the next day.
[SPEAKER_01]: No work, no duties.
[SPEAKER_01]: Villagers would do anything that kuti needs, like, kuti needs repairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he would go there on these, like, you know, couple of weeks or longer, and always have, like, an expiry date, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, in 10 days would always set something up that would require him to go, I don't know,
[SPEAKER_01]: ...to the town, or to this place, or to that place, and then he would come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was doing that, and in the meantime, while he was there, he would go up in the path, do the chores, and then spend the entire afternoon watching the nostrils, doing the ānāpānasati, or sensations, or whatever technique he got into.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the time comes when he can go, and then he would feel, okay, now I can go, I did my work, and then he would go back and repeat that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, on one occasion, one of his plans fell through,
[SPEAKER_01]: And the person was supposed to pick him up, I don't know, Friday or something, and he didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they said next Friday.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by that point, he he was actually quite, you know, built up this tension, he couldn't sit anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just the thought of having to spend another day meditating, was just filled him with anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, the natural kind of conclusion is, well, I don't have to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, now that filled him with even greater anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: What will I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I sat for, like, ten days now, six hours a day every afternoon, till the evening, then I go to sleep, then pin the pad, then I sit six days, then six hours, then I go to sleep, then get up, pin the pad, do the chores, sit, and... and just got tired of that routine, couldn't do it anymore, and it's like, well, I don't have to sit, and now the panic really set in.
[SPEAKER_01]: What will I do for the remaining of my time?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he panicked and then on the next day he basically came to Hillside to visit us.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was quite quite distraught and wanted to talk and, you know, because I think part of him was shocked.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he thought he was doing the right practices.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was doing all these techniques that all these great Ajahns teach and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you still can't be with yourself, what use is any of that to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: If, like, if you're not able to do it, or if there's, say, sounds, or, like, I don't know, you end up in a hospital or something, and you can't do your... your... your calming practices, your management techniques, what use is that to you, when your mind will go back to its own wilderness, and able to pressure and threaten you, and overwhelm you?
[SPEAKER_01]: To the point that you run in panic.
[SPEAKER_01]: For any help, any advice you can get, even from people that you were usually disagreeing with.
[SPEAKER_01]: I... me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, he was... he was asking questions, listening and stuff, and I explained this to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see, like, that he understands that what I was explaining is something completely opposite of everything that he has been doing in the name of practice up to that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that was bound with the sense of duty, that was bound with the meditation, that was bound with technique, that was bound with this expectation that results will come on their own, when I diligently just fulfill this mindless practice, which also conveniently keeps me occupied, so I don't have to be with myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why you have to recognize, okay, this was like a bit of an extreme example.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, he was following all these other things that we clearly, you know, and repeatedly describe as wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if you don't go to that extreme, you might still be doing the right stuff, you know, listening to Hillside or doing the Hillside way for the same reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, in the beginning you have to learn, you have to apply, you have to, like, re-evaluate and think and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point comes when you recognize, you're in seclusion, and you will recognize, am I doing these things now because I really don't know what am I supposed to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or it's because I have this urgent pressure that needs something, mine needs something to be occupied with?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have to be careful to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you begin to truly find comfort and delight in pure seclusion of, like, non-activity, non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what outlines the mind and cittanimitta sufficiently, thoroughly, and so on, for the fulfillment of the right view and everything else that follows.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only then, you can go to Migjala Sutta and recognize these subtler attitudes of non-delighting in that which has a reason, with the delightful thing that has a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not craving, not welcoming, not accepting the thing that's there on its own and being able to see that space between.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because before that, it's like something arises, I must either act towards it or try and deny it, destroy it, choke it out, asphyxiate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And none of those actions or reactions, whether it's a lust or aversion, both or rather both of those directions, do not reveal and further obscure the mind, the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wear your attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, what the Sutta describes like that, he doesn't welcome, he doesn't delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: That describes an attitude, your attitude, towards your own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's something that's not seen for as long as you're engaged positively or negatively with sight, sounds, smell, taste, touches and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the whole point of being first withdrawn, not distracting yourself, so that the mind can, like, be seen, can reveal itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you could basically start learning, as I said in other talks, how to talk to it and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I did write down a list of, say, somebody who is trying to develop seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, layperson or monk, it doesn't really matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to wait until...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can start looking at my mind, or looking for my mind, or trying to discern my mind, only when I can be alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, you start doing that all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that the periods, the actual periods of physical seclusion will be necessary to discern those signs correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, if you have not already been working in that direction, no amount of signs will magically reveal themselves on account of you just being alone, suddenly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to start working in that direction, the point is to start pretty much undermining the attitudes that are keeping you bound.
[SPEAKER_01]: With association, with the need for association and company, finding safety in those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's like, again, no magic pill, no magic technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to just start drilling, questioning, contemplation and reflection until those attitudes are sufficiently undermined and redirected and emphasized elsewhere towards seclusion and withdrawal from those very things that obstruct the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was asking...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you seek company,
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, you're fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you can't help it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't help but want company.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you do so, instead of just taking it at face value and seeking company, start asking yourself certain questions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Start revealing more about that attitude, that kind of pressuring mood behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're seeking company, why are you doing so?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you trying to get rid of?
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you're gonna get a relief, some form of relief, by seeking company.
[SPEAKER_01]: But relief from what?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that you need to be relieved from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you'll see the answer to all this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, again, seeking company obscures the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obscure the mind, no sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop seeking company, or rather, you're seeking company because the pressure of your own mind is something you want to be relieved from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the animal is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Allowing it to be closer to me, it's even more unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let me just distract myself and postpone and procrastinate and, you know, I'll deal with it later.
[SPEAKER_01]: And unless you start questioning that attitude, it's never gonna disappear magically on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to start bringing it up whenever you desire a company, want to choose the association and distraction through the means of others,
[SPEAKER_01]: You actually don't act out on that and start questioning and revealing what is the underlying thing that I'm trying to relieve myself from.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it really that unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, if it is, that's... again, that should be a reason for concern.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means I'm unpleasant to myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't live with my own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need others.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need association.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need company.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need...
[SPEAKER_01]: I need connections, because otherwise, I cannot live with myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's... that should be the most concerning thing to everybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, say, on the other hand, there is no company, there is no option for company.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are... just happen to be alone, nothing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the underlying tension, like, beneath that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there like a building up of restlessness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there like a discomfort that's pushing you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I must do this, I must do that, I must occupy... Again, don't take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ask yourself, okay, so this is factually what I'm feeling, this is factually what mind is pushing me towards, but I don't need to act upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to automatically distract myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how justifiable it seems.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me just
[SPEAKER_01]: For just a short period of time, actually question this attitude, as opposed to how I always just do, accept it, and act out of it, and mask it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is it that I'm trying to run away from, if I seek things to do, when there's nothing to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, let me not do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me just sit with this.
[SPEAKER_01]: See how far it will go.
[SPEAKER_01]: See what other things will mind start throwing at me as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's the true meditation, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, obviously, you could say... say you're doing all of this now, then another line of reflection you can have is like... so, can I... can I remember, can I recognize the actual peacefulness or at least some aspect of when I was alone, not distracting myself with duties or actions and so on, not choosing company,
[SPEAKER_01]: Overall, it doesn't feel right, doesn't feel pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am pushed and pressured to... boredom is building up, but is there any aspect of that that I could recollect or, you know, kind of re-evaluate and actually recognize it as agreeable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Overall, yes, it's not going to be agreeable, not in the beginning, but are there any aspects of it that I could factually say, oh, but no, that was actually agreeable, that I do prefer that aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that, yeah, when you're alone, okay, well, you don't have to deal with others, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to try as hard to not lose the context, because the simple non-engagement with others means maintenance of the context, even if you're not making the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are there any other?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aspects... however, like, brief or fleeting, of the actual seclusion, set up rightly, that you could recall as pleasant and agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yes, recall them more often than not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try and... try and spread them... spread them around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplate them, so they become even more pronounced.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of just, obviously, focusing on the negative pressure of the boredom and the restless mind that's trying to get you to... to act out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of that is pretty much to start revealing these, you know, tones, backgrounds, context, frameworks, moods, whatever you want to call it, which is what your citta is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, everybody has the thoughts of what the citta is, thoughts and the mental perceptions of the citta, but for as long as you're not withdrawn rightly from sensuality, withdrawn rightly from the dependence on company, those thoughts will always be abstractions.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, they have nothing to land on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once, say, you are withdrawn rightly from sensuality and do the practices and reflections we just described, then you can recognize that
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there is an enduring mood, there is an enduring tone, that background kind of influence, and that's what citta is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you recognize that, even more specific signs and features and kind of indications of that tone become palpable now, become visible, become recognizable, become relatable, become concrete, not abstract, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could then, simply through, like, not even verbalizing the question, just thinking about what is the state of that tone, what is the inclination, what is the leaning, you will already know the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're already seeing your mind much more acutely than before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, those would be, like, the reflections, as I said, that one can do
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to develop and then continue developing that seclusion correctly, that can outline the mind and then obviously eventually uproot all the subtle attitudes between you and the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, obviously, on the basis of this sutta, I have some more questions that are kind of more like technical and stuff, so I'll go through them as well, because I think, you know, different people come from different backgrounds, different sides, different levels of knowledges and familiarity, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's a question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody says, like, so, when person is seclusion and then, you know, you have your mind coming up with dialogues, with questions and answers and dialogues, inner dialogues.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, does that mean you're dwelling in company or is it you're simply distracting yourself or it's not a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's always going to be something that I think most people will encounter quite soon, probably.
[SPEAKER_01]: As soon as you start with drawing, then you're going to be in these mental scenarios and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the point is, you have to kind of recognize, is there pressure behind those dialogues?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there like a like a certain kind of necessive imperative?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I must finish this dialogue in my mind that is forcing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, basically, yeah, like you will be distracting yourself with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be pretty much dwelling in company, because usually it's gonna...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it doesn't necessarily involve, you know, images of other people, or like trying to finish conversation with somebody else, if you're just talking to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're doing it out of that, I've really got to finish this conversation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to be a distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole point of seclusion is to reveal that pressure, and that pressure can only be uprooted if you stop acting out of it whenever you recognize it, endure it on the right level, and then not feed it until more of the mind nimittas are revealed behind that pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because every pressure there is... hides the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, more pressure hides even more of the mind, like full-on blown pressure of sensuality acting out of sensuality will really obscure the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you're not going to be magically just able to tell your mind instantly to stop having these conversations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But whenever, you know, you lapse and then you regain certain context of what's happening, you try like, okay, no, I won't feel this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the mind really wants you to finish the sentence for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll stay with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how up here it feels.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, another question is, like, says, based on Udāna 4.1 Megīya Sutta, that Sutta says that if someone does not yet have the right view, they should at least keep contact with somebody, somebody who does, in order to develop the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's that part of the utterance of another.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if you are in a position to be instructed by somebody else who has developed the right view or more, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, the time will come where you have to do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this simply means if somebody who is still learning,
[SPEAKER_01]: Who is really still not sure about what they should be doing in terms of the practice, when they're still stabbing in the dark or trying everything eclectic kind of collection of techniques and practices and not really seeing, you know, whether they contradict each other or the suttas and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that person, like, they can't just go in seclusion and expect magical kind of crystallization of all the truths and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, they need to learn.
[SPEAKER_01]: They still need to learn, they still need to to ponder, re-evaluate, use their intellect to kind of remove as many obstructions of the views as possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what this sutta refers to.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Megia.
[SPEAKER_01]: Megia Sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, they need to keep in contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you know, if you have access to books, talks, questions, you don't need to be physically with that person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Back in the day, that was the only way of learning.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you couldn't get an mp3 player and listen to your talks in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... so, the question this person is asking is that, eh... at the practical level, for putrījānās and lay persons, external seclusion should mean just some brief periods in a day or certain periods in a monastery in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one of those?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, both.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you can get.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even seclusion during periods of day.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the point to learn how to then not distract yourself when there is nothing to do and really see these kind of undertones that that are generally pressuring you throughout the day
[SPEAKER_01]: Set up these directions for your actions, for your cravings, for your neuroses, anxieties, all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're always there, known, but they're just obscured.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why in seclusion you would be revealing that, by not practicing distraction and by not, kind of, as I said, falling back into the dependence on company and so on and having something to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the second question was, how does one know whether a particular sutta is for putrugenas or noble disciples?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, some suttas are clear, but some suttas are not so clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, well, you could just safely assume that unless the Sutta clearly says and talks about non-dhamma, as in, like, rebirths in heavens and how to look after your wives and family and be a good businessman, those are for putujanas and have nothing to do with the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ones that deal with the practice, unless it specifically says that whether, you know, putujana, whether a householder or a noble disciple, this is what they should do,
[SPEAKER_01]: You should assume that it's all already taught to somebody who is either sotāpanna or at least meets the requirements for, as we just described.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the signs of the mind, which is the prerequisite for sotāpārthi and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, like, have withdrawn themselves from the physical engagement with sensuality, acting out of will, and live restrained by the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That, obviously, doesn't mean that you shouldn't try to understand those suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the whole point of studying any and all suttas is to understand the core principle behind the practice, which is why... which is how you will stop being a patujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, if a puṭṭhujana who is not withdrawn, doesn't keep the precept, is not celibate, is not... does not practice... learn how to become sort of... how to delight in seclusion, no amount of study in and of itself will make you understand the principle of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the prerequisites need to be met.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you meet the prerequisites and really fortify yourself in those prerequisites, you still need an external instruction, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: the right instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, factually, you will need a lot less.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you would have removed a lot of dust from your eyes, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha had a preference in the beginning to teach those people they were closest to understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because saves him time, saves him effort, saves him the hassle.
[SPEAKER_01]: They already did the work of withdrawing themselves and pretty much training their mind in many regards, many respects.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just needed to, like, like, straighten a few things and it would all fall into place, because they did 90% of the actual work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, both things need to be developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you read the suttas, you try to understand them, but don't just think that satipaṭṭhi will come on account of some magical... even if it's a factual insight, even if it's not like magical meditation experience of self-hypnosis or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's an actual insight, like, oh, wow, you understood something you've been reading.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now understand it a thousand more times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep drilling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep getting more things to understand and pair them with a lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pair them with withdrawal and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how... that's the only way it can work.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the Noble Eightfold Path is described, for a reason, as a Noble Eightfold Path, as a gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, so somebody also asked about the term parasocial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Says, we often hear about the term parasocial these days on the internet, especially in regard to social media, and I was wondering if these types of relations could fall into enjoying company.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this person really engage in talking to people day by day.
[SPEAKER_01]: They live alone, but they wholeheartedly engage in watching streamers and youtubers that they kind of feel connected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, definitely.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think they already know the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: They ask the question maybe just to be sure about it, but, yeah, of course, like, you know, you might watch something or learn on the internet, I don't know, some practical skill or something, and even if the person is there, if you enjoy watching them, you're doing it for a reason of learning a skill.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're watching somebody just for the sake of, you know, whatever they say or do as a means of, like, hanging out with them, well, it is definitely you're not alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're dwelling in company.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same, like, you know, you start... take up... read the novels and really get emotionally invested in the characters and their lives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you're not dwelling in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are seeking all these proxies that serve as company.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you'll need to stop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And do I have more?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, so there's like a... oh, yeah, so there's a question regarding that whole
[SPEAKER_01]: We just read, if a monk doesn't delight, does not approve, does not still holding to a Saitama's meditate touches, for him delight does not arise, and he would cease, and with ceasing, the passion would cease, and the bondage would disappear, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the question says, this person says, I read this passage as restraining the sense objects properly, which is in my control, until the light ceases on the level of citta, which is not in my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they're asking, so does this mean this is like a time-bound process?
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you could be doing your restraint rightly, but the mind will not necessarily instantly calm down or abandon its craving and trying to pressure you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha would first tell somebody, go and dwell restrained by the patimokkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Become established in precepts rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Train your mind on the basis of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the basis of that domain, on the basis of that development.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, you are practicing sensory strain rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not acting out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not welcoming.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not indulging those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not trying to get rid of them out of aversion either.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not trying to get rid of the pressuring mind out of aversion either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the whole experience is, well, it's uncomfortable, because you have the mind pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The citta is still affected, infected with delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: The animal still wants to run out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're preventing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that has to be sustained until the animal calms down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not until you decide to give up and open the gates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how long does that take?
[SPEAKER_01]: That time-bound process, how long it will actually last?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you will only know, in hindsight, once the animal has calmed down.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might calm down quickly, if, whatever, for whatever reason, you didn't have that much dust in your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said today, that's highly unlikely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of those people would have already become arahants by now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is to recognize, yeah, this is
[SPEAKER_01]: Within my domain of what I can actually do, or rather not do, and sustain that, and now I have to patiently endure until the animal calms down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you know, all the similes about the elephant and the thoroughbred horse and getting the elephant out of the wilderness and tying it down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, you gotta wait until it stops kicking, screaming, urinating, defecating, threatening you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when it comes down, it's like, okay,
[SPEAKER_01]: Now we can learn how to communicate directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any other allowance is a compromise.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically allowing the wilderness and there will be no training, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not respect you, as I said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's gonna feel like the state of citta and your, say, imposed restraint, not acting out, will feel, well, discrepant, will feel incompatible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, citta wants you to act.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anima wants you to give it what it wants, so to feel compatible again, because you are basically following its desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, initially, it has to feel incompatible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to feel like at odds, until the citta comes down, not until you give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's like the establishment in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's going to be sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you truly calm your citta down rightly, within that setup, that is being established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not anymore, depending on the external notions of of duty, and so on, and everything else that follows.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that that equals sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_01]: That equals thorough familiarity with signs of the mind, because you've been pressured by it for so long, without giving in, without opening the gates, without letting the elephant go back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once somebody is seeing the mind, in in the past, or in the talk, I think, that you gave, or
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, Bhante and Nika mentioned that the choice between a painful practice and a pleasurable practice is not choice, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically choice to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it feels pleasant or unpleasant, it's not up to you to decide.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, it seems quite reasonable, like, before one can, like, communicate with the mind that it is just going to be painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, maybe, would you permit that once one can sort of communicate with the mind that if they emphasize, for example, those contemplations, the body contemplation, the death contemplation, is going to be evoking more pressure versus, let's say, one who's sort of establishing pronunciation and sort of allowing the animal to enjoy its non-agitation and maybe emphasizing that aspect?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a bit of a... it seems like maybe there's a bit of a choice, sort of, once that... Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a choice like what you put forward.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want to complete the work, there is no choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: If putting forward renunciation is factually uprooting craving for you, that's why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not doing it because it's more pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: If putting forward death contemplation and everything else is undoing factually craving for you, that's why you're putting it forward.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, you're still...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start choosing the renunciation because it's more pleasant, ways of calming the mind, that means you're not putting forward things referenced by what's undoing the craving and taming the mind fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're putting forward things that's rooted in your preference, which means you're not going to fulfill the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by choosing on account of pleasure and pain, you will quite likely not fulfill the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you think that... it's kind of... like, you can emphasize maybe that aspect of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I'm sort of getting at is that, if you sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think maybe this comes back to something else you said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you have to know the time when to evoke those more difficult contexts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it's not calm already... And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to calm the mind down, if the mind is too agitated, if the mind is too agitated, you calm it by talking to it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you would have already learned some communicating skills.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, you know, you started by asking, like, once you see the mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already seeing the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody is already seeing the mind, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that that extent is insufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: Needs to be uncovered more and more and more.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, I have no idea or even even a glimpse of what the mind is or could be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I always did in those earlier videos back in Sri Lanka, those kind of direct interrogations, it was like, how are you feeling right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is your mood?
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you're overlooking.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start emphasizing something else due to the pressure of the very mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's going back to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already ways of seeing the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, to really see the signs of the mind that correctly, accurately outline it, that's then sufficient, become sufficient for developing the right view and so on, yeah, you need to do more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all these contemplations even now, that, you know, this kind of self-questions that I went through,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can start at... like anybody can... householder can already start asking those questions, because he will already know the answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, of course, the more you ask them, the more answers you're going to get from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Each time you go back to it, you're going to discover even more subtler, clearer reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: But from the start, you already have the idea of where the... what the pressure is, where... what do you pressure towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: What mood endures, regardless of whether you're getting stuff...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, you know, as I said, I often give that example, you know, when you're in a good mood, you could have people, like, being rude to you or everything, and it's like, oh, but nothing affects me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, today, my mind's happy, it doesn't matter what you say to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for whatever reason, the mind is in a good mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, got what he wanted or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, on another occasion, you could have mind in the bad mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could have people effectually around you, caring for you, trying to help you, saying the right things, and you'll be hating them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be having ill will towards them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you already know that there is a discrepancy, you already know there is something underneath you that's kind of forcing you in these directions, and then you take it for face value, and then you act out, and so on, and then you try to calm down through meditation techniques or whatever else, but that thing remains controlling you from underneath, or from inside, or whatever simile you want to use.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the point, like, to start uncovering that from the day one, because you already know that there is that thing there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not be very clear about it, it might be ambiguous, but if you start saying no to your desires, and then start increasing sense restraint when the time for it is right, and asking those questions in the meantime, it's just gonna get clearer and clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, probably, initially, it's going to get more and more and more unpleasant, because you stop running away from it, through giving in the pressure, to the pressure.
Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, finding the balance within that, to not... then, go the other direction of, like, increasing the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that will also come out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, oh, it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, well, how about I double down now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me just tighten it more, so it's done with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, now I actually have to restrain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sort of picking up the signs of how it can be calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wholesomely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Picking up the signs that when it's too tight, you should not be tightening it more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not feeling, oh, but I must... but my duty... but as suttas say, this is like... suttas can say whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know exactly why you would be doing it there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, now I won't feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's interesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... like the animal sort of doubling down on itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like it wants you to, like, harm it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not letting me go where I want to go, just kill me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just put me out of my misery.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, I was wondering if you could talk... well, maybe somebody can hear this and sort of like... it sort of almost starts to sound like management a bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, you talk to the mind and then just drops the pressure and then like you sort of... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can sort of lean that way and just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, I wanted to hear your thoughts about that and, you know, the difference between that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, again, as I said, you won't be able to avoid management.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's important is to not fall into a view that management is the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know what the goal is,
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're trying to do it as accurately, as correctly as possible, which is not going to be possible from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, doesn't matter how accurately you try to do it, it's... you're going to be doing it for the reasons of management.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at least you are aiming at the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's going to be always a mixture of a bit of... there's like 10% of it is right, but the 90% is management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it's going to be like less management, more accurate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it's going to be all management.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you work with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you know that, fundamentally, you don't want to have to do anything for you to not suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't obscure that goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't say, no, no, no, that's not the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: The goal is always do the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the mind is like this, I do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the mind is like that, I'm fine with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm happy with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you will never then abandon management.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but if you know that that's not the goal, then, of course, everything you do is going to be like, as I said, mix, a bit of management, a bit of this, sometimes more, sometimes less.
[SPEAKER_01]: But your aim is to reach, to develop to the extent whereby you won't have to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't even have to talk to the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't even have to issue any commands to the dog, to my dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indeed, in any circumstance, it does the right thing by not doing the wrong things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, so the communication is not... or it's based on the understanding that it's, like, to uproot it, not to just, like, constantly playing with the mind when it moves.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, it's to teach it to not move in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that's already the fundamental message and there is no more communication necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will know for itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will know that it knows for itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you would be liberated, completed the task, no more... nothing else for you to do, as the suttas describe in Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't even have to talk to your mind anymore, ever again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplating, conceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thinking about, for example, Earth and
[SPEAKER_00]: That is how that finds a footing through the direct attention or sort of subjection.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I was kind of wondering about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there's the conceiving, and through the conceiving, it's like that phenomena finds a footing into... it's like you have a relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's like a subjection created through... through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the basis for conceiving?
[SPEAKER_00]: The image?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or... vision?
[SPEAKER_00]: With the image?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I mean, in a sense, what's the... what's the reason that conceivings are there?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could say, yeah, elements find footing because of the conceivings, but because of what the conceivings are there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you conceiving something you just do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Something can switch on and off or something?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would... maybe to bring it more on the level of, like, pressure, I guess.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is there pressure there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why is that phenomena there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or why is that touching?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, why is there a pressure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why there can be a pressure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, pressure is not something you can switch on and off or choose to not do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose I would have to say it's the mind, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that... it's not tamed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so why is the mind not tamed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have a...
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you play part...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, there's not like a direct... Do you... Do you play any part in the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ultimately.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we just did what many suttas would do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start with a question and then, by questioning the right thing, you come to the actual thing that you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how does the earth find the footing in me and... Oh, it's because of the conceivings, because of the pressure, because of the wild mind, because of my actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore,
[SPEAKER_01]: You conceive Earth because of your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You conceive in Earth, from Earth, apart from... because of your actions, by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now somebody can take that like a commentary and study the list and create an Abhidhamma around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or somebody can actually say, okay, what actions?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me not perpetuate those actions anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me undo the conceivings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, the time will come later on, where maybe you can directly, you know, not conceive earth in earth and have that subtle movements very familiar with.
[SPEAKER_01]: But 99% of that is the actions by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: The three layers, which is what maintains the whole pressure, craving, conceivings, are all symptoms of actions rooted in ignorance, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Interesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's a good way to, let's say, look at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it seems that, I'd want to say, the untamed mind pushes for that ayoniso in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, wants to maintain itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you go with the flow, with the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to start going against that very grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's actually where the
[SPEAKER_00]: Undoing happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I remember there was a talk where you did this exact thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: One of the monks, I think it might have been Yanadipo, was talking about the conceivings.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might have been in the wild atmospheres, I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But basically, you just brought it down to why are those conceivings there in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like,
[SPEAKER_00]: It is those actions that are perpetuating the conceivings.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you undo the conceivings.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of important, like even when you know that, it's it's important to to remind yourself of it or to be reminded of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, it's like when there's like an acute acute pressure to think about resolve conceivings or this or that or wrap your head around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kind of know, okay, there is pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That I have learned now, that I shouldn't act out of, but this justifies it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you still choose to put that which you should put first, you put it a second, and oh, okay, no, I'll... it justifies it, I'll deal with this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, that's why, even if you get the right answer, quote-unquote, and write the right paper on concealings... You're making it worse, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, at least, you're certainly not not making it better.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not going to be any closer to uprooting conceivings, because you still very much, when the choice is presented, you choose to act out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You choose to give in to it and follow it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is asking you to re-clarify it and get the answer and like, that whatever, that pleasure, it's sort of seeking from, you know, sort of contemplation and, oh, you know, that's the insight and etc.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're very right.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a good point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is a very blatant thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like you sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically sensuality anyway, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that... Well, fundamentally, yeah, the central being, the central domain, the extent of the craving determines that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also, see, you start understanding it like this and then it becomes a lot clearer how there were people in the suttas that were literally just told
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you know, it's rooted in passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This passion falls out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They went to seclusion and fulfilled the goal of the Buddha's dispensation and became arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: They actually stuck to it and worked their way through it in the correct manner, did not act out of things they shouldn't act out, protected things they should protect, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of everything else that Buddha talked about, all these symptoms and stuff, fell off, never to return.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite interesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe, over time, it seems in your teachings even, like, if you go and read meanings or maybe the earlier discussions, there seems to be that sort of emphasis, but then it seems like, at a certain point, you just cut that out and you said, like, maybe this exact problem that you're talking, that we're talking about now, sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, in the beginning, you know, I've announced the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter where people were coming from, but after a while, and you do it for a few years, it's like, okay, I, you know, I have to be as efficient as possible, because I cannot be repeating myself 20 years down the line, just saying the same stuff, without any effect or benefit to a person, just basically just satisfying their curiosities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you start to tailor, like, talk about things that matter and bring down, bring everything back down to where actually the difference can be made.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whether people choose to follow it or not, that's fine, but I know that if they follow it, they will arrive at the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, if you just give them the answer, to whatever angle they came from, it does not necessarily guarantee they will make the actual effort that needs to be made, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, initially, you do need answers, you do need to learn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, Yanavera was very useful for me, although, yes, he was also just on the level of theoretical answers for as far as anybody comes to read it, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was doing the lifestyle of it, but that's not something you could have just emulated through reading his books.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where many people fall into the trap of just writing papers and quoting Yanavera and being convinced he's the most right person in the world, but they're not taught upon as themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is necessary and useful, especially because everybody comes with lots of preconceived notions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, the point is, there is a more direct way to deal with the preconceived notions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start taming your mind, which is all, like, well documented in the suttas,
[SPEAKER_01]: Start questioning your preconceived notions, your disagreements, your little preferences, and you will arrive at the obvious that you kind of know, which is why you were resisting what I'm saying from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not you specifically, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: When people try to... well, this and that, you already know.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were authentic, transparent enough, you would know why you were resisting the gradual training that we describe, the way we describe, the way the suttas describe it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you don't want it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want your preferences to be served, because this is too frightening, too scary, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just need some transparency.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it would have saved me a lot of time, and I'm trying to save other people time, by telling them that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You question everything, including your own stances, and you will arrive at the transparency.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to feel pleasant, but it's certainly going to position you a lot better for actually then understanding what the essence of the Buddha's teaching was and the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I think that's really important to go back and sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep that emphasis in mind, especially because within, let's say, the phenomenological Buddhist circle, there's that sort of vibe to just, like, figure these things out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can see things, get distracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, it's not like, I must stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when you want to think about, instead of just taking it at face value, broaden the context and recognize the experience as a whole of wanting to think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: See the underlying pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't just take it and go with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Include it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Include it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.